We really need to put the best we have to offer within reach of our children.
يجب علينا حقاً جعل أفضل ما لدينا في متناول يد أطفالنا
If we don't do that, we're going to get the generation we deserve.
إذا لم نفعل ذلك, سنحصل على الجيل الذي نستحق
They're going to learn from whatever it is they have around them.
سوف يتعلمون من أي شيء حولهم
And we, as now the elite, parents, librarians, professionals, whatever it is,
و نحن كوننا, النخبة, الآباء, امناء المكتبات, المحترفون, أيا كان,
a bunch of our activities are, in fact, in trying to get the best we have to offer
مجموعة من نشاطاتنا هي في الحقيقة محاولة جعل أفضل ما لدينا
within reach of those around us, or as broadly as we can.
بمتناول أولئك الذين من حولنا أو أوسع شريحة ممكنة
I'm going to start and end this talk with a couple things that are carved in stone.
سأستهل و أنهي هذا الحديث بشيئين منقوشين على الحجر
One is what's on the Boston Public Library.
"مجاني للجميع", هي إحداهما المنقوشة
Carved above their door is, "Free to All."
فوق باب مكتبة بوسطن العامة
It's kind of an inspiring statement,
انه نص يبعث على الالهام
and I'll go back at the end of this.
و سأعود اليه في نهاية الحديث
I'm a librarian, and what I'm trying to do is bring all of the works of knowledge
أنا أمين مكتبة, وما أحاول أن أفعله أن أجعل كل أعمال المعرفة بمتناول
to as many people as want to read it.
أكبر عدد ممكن من الراغبين بقراءتها
And the idea of using technology is perfect for us.
و فكرة استخدام التكنولوجيا هي مثالية لنا
I think we have the opportunity to one-up the Greeks.
اعتقد لدينا الفرصة لنتفوق على اليونانيين
It's not easy to one-up the Greeks. But with the industriousness of the Egyptians,
ليس من السهل التفوق على اليونانيين. ولكنهم استطاعوا بناء مكتبة الاسكندرية
they were able to build the Library of Alexandria --
بمجهود المصريين
the idea of a copy of every book of all the peoples of the world.
فكرة نسخ كل كتاب من جميع الناس في العالم
The problem was you actually had to go to Alexandria to go to it.
المشكلة كانت أنه توجب عليك الذهاب فعلاً الى الاسكندرية للذهاب للمكتبة.
On the other hand, if you did, then great things happened.
ولكن بالمقابل اذا فعلت فإن أموراً عظيمة حدثت.
I think we can one-up the Greeks and achieve something.
اعتقد انه بامكاننا التفوق على اليونانيين و تحقيق شيئ ما.
And I'm going to try to argue only one point today:
و سوف أحاول اليوم أن أحاور حول نقطة واحدة هي:
that universal access to all knowledge is within our grasp.
أن الولوج العالمي لكل المعرفة هو في قبضتنا
So if I'm successful, then you'll actually come away thinking,
لذلك اذا كنت ناجحأ, فسوف تغادر مفكرأً
yeah, we could actually achieve the great vision of everything ever published,
نعم , يمكننا فعلاً تحقيق الرؤية العظيمة أن يكون كل ما تم نشره
everything that was ever meant for distribution,
و كل ما أعد للتوزيع
available to anybody in the world that's ever wanted to have access to it.
متاحاً لأي شخص في العالم يرغب في الوصول اليه
Yes, there's issues about how money should be distributed,
نعم, هناك مسائل حول كم من المال ينبغي صرفه
and that's still being refigured out.
وذلك ما زال يبحث فيه
But I'd say there's plenty of money, and there's plenty of demand,
ولكن ما أرغب بقوله أنه هناك الكثير من المال و الكثير من الطلب
so we can actually achieve that.
لذلك يمكننا حقأً تحقيقه
But I'm going to go over the technological, social
و لكن سأقوم باستعراض الجوانب التقنية و الاجتماعية
and sort of where are we as a whole, trying to get to that particular vision.
و نوعاً ما اين نحن الان في إطار المحاولة للوصول لتلك الرؤية المحددة.
And the way I'm going to try to do this is do it like the Amazon.com website,
و الطريقة التي سأحاول بها فعل ذلك هي أن أفعلها بطريقة مشابهة لموقع أمازون Amazon.com
the books, music, video and just go step -- media type by media type,
من ناحية الكتب, الموسيقى, الفيديو و كخطوة أبعد , حسب نوعية الميديا
just go and say, all right, how're we doing on this?
يمكنك الذهاب و القول, حسناً كيف نعمل على ذلك؟
So if we start with books, you know, sort of where are we?
اذا ما بدأنا بالكتب, نوعاً ما , أين نحن؟
Well, first you have to, as an engineer, scope the problem. How big is it?
حسناً, كمهندس عليك في البداية أن تستهدف المشكلة. ما هو حجمها؟
If you wanted to put all of the published works online
كم سيكون حجم المشكلة اذا أردت
so that anybody could have it available, well, how big a problem is it?
أن تضع جميع الأعمال المنشورة بحيث تكون متاحة لأي شخص على الانترنت؟
Well, we don't really know, but the largest print library in the world
حسناً, نحن لا نعرف تماماً, ولكن أضخم مكتبة كتب مطبوعة في العالم
is the Library of Congress. It's 26 million volumes, 26 million volumes.
هي مكتبة الكونغرس -- 26 مليون مجلد,
It is, by far and away, the largest print library in the world.
إن 26 مليون مجلد يجعلها أضخم مكتبة كتب مطبوعة في العالم
And a book, if you had a book, is about a megabyte,
وحسب ما تعلم إذا كنت تملك كتاباً بصيغة Microsoft Word
so -- you know, if you had it in Microsoft Word.
فإن حجمه حوالي ميغابايت واحد
So a megabyte, 26 million megabytes is 26 terabytes --
لذلك, 26 مليون ميغابايت يعطي 26 تيرابايت
it goes mega-, giga-, tera-. 26 terabytes.
ذلك يسير باتجاه ميغا, غيغا, تيرا, 26 تيرا بايت.
26 terabytes fits in a computer system that's about this big,
تتسع 26 تيرا بايت في نظام كمبيوتر تقريباً بهذا الحجم
on spinning Linux drives, and it costs about 60,000 dollars.
على سواقات لينوكس الدوارة, و تكلفتها بحدود 60,000 دولار
So for the cost of a house -- or around here, a garage --
يعني بكلفة بيت أو تقريباً مرآب
you can put, you can have spinning all of the words in the Library of Congress.
يمكنك وضع -- و يمكنك الاحتفاظ بجميع الكلمات في مكتبة الكونغرس
That's pretty neat.
هذا أنيق حقاً
Then the question is, what do you get?
السؤال لاحقاً هو: على ماذا حصلت؟
You know, is it worth trying to get there?
هل يستحق المحاولة للحصول عليه؟
Do you actually want it online?
هل تريده حقاً على الانترنت؟
Some of the first things that people do is they make book readers
بعض الامور الاولى التي يفعلها الناس هو أن يصنعوا قارئ كتب
that allow you to search inside the books, and that's kind of fun.
يمكنك من البحث داخل الكتب, و هذا ممتع
And you can download these things, and look around them in new and different ways.
و يمكنك تنزيل هذه الأمور و البحث فيهم بطرق جديدة و مختلفة
And you can get at them remotely, if you happen to have a laptop.
و يمكنك الحصول عليهم عن بعد, اذا حدث و كان لديك كمبيوتر محمول
There's starting to be some of these sort of page turn-y interfaces
هناك بدأت وصلات تعديل الصفحات التي تشبه
that look a whole lot like books in certain ways,
إلى حد كبير الكتب بطرق محددة بالظهور.
and you can search them, make little tabs, and it's kind of cute --
و يمكنك البحث فيهم, وضع تبويبات صغيرة و مازالت
still very book-like -- on your laptop.
شديدة الشبه بالكتاب على كمبيوترك المحمول
But I don't know, reading things on a laptop --
و لكن لا أعلم, القراءة من اكمبيوتر المحمول--
whenever I pull up my laptop, it always feels like work.
كلما سحبت جهازي لأقرأ فإنه يعطي شعوراً أنني في العمل
I think that's one of the reasons why the Kindle is so great.
أعتقد أنه أحد الأسباب كون جهاز كندل رائع
I don't have to feel like I'm at work to read a Kindle.
لا يتوجب علي أن أشعر أنني في العمل لأقرأ من كندل
It's starting to be a little bit more specified.
لقد أصبح أكثر تحدديداً بشكل قليل
But I have to say that there's older technologies that I tend to like.
ولكن علي القول أن هناك تقنية أقدم أميل اليها
I like the physical book.
أنا أحب الكتب الورقية
And I think we can go and use our technology to go and digitize things,
و أظننا قادرين على الذهاب و استخدام تقنيتنا لرقمنة الأشياء
put them on the Net, and then download,
ورفعهم على الانترنت و من ثم تنزيلهم
print them and bind them, and end up with books again.
طباعتهم وتجليدهم و الحصول على الكتب في النهاية مرة أخرى
And we sort of said, well, how hard is this?
و نحن نوعاً ما نقول حسناً هل كان ذلك صعباً
And it turns out to not be very hard.
و نكتشف أنه ليس صعباً جداً
We actually went off to make a bookmobile.
نحن فعلاً انصرفنا لصنع مكتبة متجولة
And a bookmobile -- the size of a van with a satellite dish,
و المكتبة المتجولة -- بحجم سيارة فان مع صحن لاقط صناعي
a printer, binder and cutter, and kids make their own books.
وطابعة, عدة تجليد و قطاعة والنتيجة أن الأطفال يصنعون كتبهم الخاصة
It costs about three dollars to download, print and bind a normal, old book.
إن تنزيل وطباعة و تغليف كتاب قديم عادي يكلف ثلاث دولارات
And they actually come out kind of nice looking.
و هم حقاً يظهرون بشكل جميل
You can actually get really good-looking books
يمكنك حقاً الحصول على كتب جميلة المظهر
for on the order of one penny per page, sort of the parts cost for doing this.
بتكلفة بنس واحد للصفحة كنوع من تكلفة الأجزاء اللازمة لعمل ذلك
So the idea of -- this technology actually may end up
لذلك فإن فكرة هذه التقنية في الواقع ستؤدي في النهاية
putting books back in people's hands again.
لوضع الكتب مرة أخرى بين أيدي الناس
There are some other bookmobiles running around.
تقوم بعض المكتبات المتنقلة الأخرى حالياً بالتجوال
This is Eric Eldred making books at Walden Pond -- Thoreau's works.
هذا ايريك ايلديرد يقوم بصنع الكتب في والدن بوند, أعمال ثورو
This is just before he got kicked out by the Parks Services,
ذلك تماماً قبل أن يطرده عمال خدمات الحدائق
for competing with the bookstore there.
لمنافسته مع محل بيع الكتب هناك
In India, they've got another couple bookmobiles running around.
في الهند, يوجد هناك بضع من المكتبات المتنقلة تقوم بالتجوال
And this is the opening day at the Library of Alexandria,
و هذا هو يوم الافتتاح في مكتبة الاسكندرية
the new Library of Alexandria, in Egypt.
المكتبة الجديدة للاسكندرية في مصر
It was quite popularly attended.
كان الحضور شعبياً للغاية
And kids starting to make their own books,
و الأطفال كانوا يعملون كتبهم الخاصة
and a happy kid with the first book that he's ever owned.
و طفل سعيد بأول كتاب يمتلكه أبداً
So the idea of being able to use this technology
لذلك فإن فكرة أن تكون قادراً على استخدام هذه التقنية
to end up with paper where I can handle sort of sounds a little retro,
لتنتهي بالورق الذي استطيع التعامل معه تبدو رجعية نوعاً ما
but I think it still has its place.
و لكن ما أزال أعتقد أن لها مكاناً
And being from the Silicon Valley, sort of utopian
و أن تكون نوعاً ما من وادي السيليكون , نوعاً من المجتمع الأمثل
sort of world,
و -- نوعاً ما العالم
we thought, if we can make this technology work in rural Uganda,
فكرنا أنه إذا كان بإمكاننا جعل هذه التقنية تعمل في قرى أوغندة
we might have something.
ربما سنحصل على شيئ ما
So we actually got some funding from the World Bank to try it out.
لذلك حصلنا فعلاً على تمويل من بنك وورلد لاختبار الفكرة
And we found in about 30 days we could go and take a couple folks from Silicon Valley,
ووجدنا أنه في غضون 30 يوم استطعنا الذهاب والحصول على شخصين من وادي السيليكون
fly them to Uganda, buy a car, set up the first Internet connection
نقلناهم بالطائرة لأوغندا, اشترينا سيارة , واسسنا أول اتصال بشبكة الانترنت
at the National Library of Uganda, figure out what they wanted,
من داخل مكتبة أوغندة الوطنية, و حددنا ماذا يريدون
and get a program going making books in rural Uganda.
و جعلنا برنامج عمل الكتب يسير في قرى أوغندة
And it actually -- so technologically, it works.
و في الحقيقة-- بشكل تقني بحت, إنه يعمل
What we found out of this is we didn't have the right books.
الذي وجدناه من ذلك هو أننا لم نكن نملك الكتب الملائمة
So the books were in the library. We could get it to people, if they're digitized,
و كذلك أيضاً الكتب الموجودة في المكتبة. يمكننا ان نقدم المكتبة للناس اذا كانت الكتب مرقمنة
but we didn't know how to quite get them digitized.
ولكننا لم نعلم كيفية رقمنتهم
Everybody thought the answer is, send things to India and China.
ارسال تلك الأشياء للصين أو الهند كان تفكير الجميع
And so we've tried that, and I'll go over that in a moment.
لذلك فقد حاولنا ذلك, و سوف استعرضه في غضون دقيقة
There are some newer technologies for delivering
يوجد هناك بعض التقنيات الاحدث لنقوم بنقلها
that have happened that are actually quite exciting as well.
و التي توافق و أنها مثيرة أيضاً
One is a print-on-demand machine that looks like a Rube Goldberg machine.
احداها هي آلة الطباعة عند الطلب, التي تبدو كآلة روب غولدبيرغ
We have one of these things now. It's completely cool.
لدينا واحدة من هذه الأشياء الآن. انها ظريفة جداً
It's all conveyor belt, and it makes a book.
انها كلها حزام ناقل و تعمل الكتب.
And it's called the "Espresso Book Machine,"
و تدعى: آلة الكتب الإسبريسو (نوع من القهوة السريعة)
and in about 10 minutes, you can press a button and make a book.
و في غضون 10 دقائق يمكنك ضغط الزر و الحصول على كتاب
Something else I'm quite excited about in this particular domain,
هناك شيئ آخر يبهجني في هذا المجال
beyond these sort of kiosk-y things where you can get books on demand,
ما وراء هذه الأكشاك حيث يمكنك الحصول على الكتب حسب الطلب
is some of these new little screens that are coming out.
انها بعض هذه الشاشات الجديدة الصغيرة التي تظهر
And one of my favorites in this is the $100 laptop.
وواحدة من أفضلها هو الكمبيوتر المحمول ذو كلفة 100 دولار
And I don't mean to steal any thunder here,
و لا أنوي هنا أن أفسد الأمر
but we've gone and used one of these things to be an e-book reader.
و لكن جعلنا من واحدة من هذه الأشياء قارئ كتب الكترونية
So here's one of the beta units and you can --
و هنا واحدة من هذه النماذج التجريبية ويمكنك--
it actually turns out to be a really good-looking e-book reader.
انها يمكن أن تصير قارئ كتب الكترونية جميلة المظهر حقاً
And we have a quick hack that we did to try to put one of our books on it,
و لدينا محاولة قرصنة سريعة أننا حاولنا وضع أحد كتبنا عليه
and it turns out that 200 dots per inch
و لوحظ أن 200 نقطة في الانش
means that you can put scanned books on them that look really good.
تعني أنه يمكنك وضع كتاب ممسوح ضوئياً فيهم و يبدون جيدين فعلاً
At 200 dots per inch, it's kind of the equivalent of a 300 dot print laser printer.
عند 200 نقطة للبوصة, انه نوعاً ما مساوٍ لـ 300 نقطة للبوصة مطبوعة بطابعة ليزر
We're in good enough shape.
نحن الان بهيئة جيدة كفاية
You actually can go and read scanned books quite easily.
يمكنك حقاً الذهاب و قراءة الكتب الممسوحة بشكل سهل جداً
So the idea of electronic books is starting to come about.
لذلك فإن فكرةالكتب الالكترونية بصدد تغيير مسارها
But how do you go about doing all this scanning?
و لكن كيف يمكنك اجراء كل هذا المسح الضوئي؟
So we thought, okay, well, let's try out this send books to India thing.
لذلك فكرنا, حسناً دعونا نحاول ارسال الكتب الى الهند
And there was a project with, funded by the National Science Foundation --
و كان هنالك مشروع-- ممول من قبل مؤسسة العلوم الوطنية
sent a bunch of scanners, and the American libraries were supposed to send books.
بعض الماسحات الضوئية المرسلة, و الكتب كان يفترض ارسالها من قبل المكتبات الامريكية
Well, they didn't. They didn't want to send their books.
حسناً, انهم لم يرغبوا بارسال كتبهم
So we bought 100,000 books and sent them to India.
لذلك قمنا بشراء 100,000 كتاب و ارسلناها الى الهند
And then we learned why you don't want to send books to India.
و عنئذ عرفنا لما لا تريد ارسال الكتب للهند
The lesson we learned out of this is, scan your own books.
الدرس الذي تعلمناه هو أنه عليك مسح كتبك الخاصة
If you really care about books, you're going to scan them better,
اذا كنت حقاً مهتماً بالكتب, فانك ستقوم بمسحهم ضوئياً بشكل أفضل
especially if they're valuable books.
خاصة, اذا كانت الكتب قيمة
If they're new books and you can just, you know, butcher them,
اذا كانت الكتب حديثة تستطيع كما تعلم أن تسفك بهم
because you could just buy another one,
لأنك ببساطة يمكنك شراءهم ثانية
that's not such a big deal in terms of doing high-quality scanning.
انه ليس بالشأن الكبير لعمل مسح ضوئي عالي الجودة
But do things that you love.
ولكن اعمل الأشياء التي تحبها
But the Indians have been scanning a lot of their own books --
و لكن الهنود قاموا بمسح الكثير من كتبهم الخاصة ---
about 300,000 now -- doing very well.
حوالي 300,000 للآن --- انهم يقومون بعمل جيد جداً
The Chinese did over a million, and the Egyptians are about 30,000.
الصينيون انهوا ما ينوف عن مليون كتاب و المصريون تقريباً 30,000
But we sent -- thought, OK, if we're going to need to do this, let's do it in-library.
ولكننا أرسلنا -- أظنه لا بأس اذا كنا سنحتاج القيام بذلك, دعونا نقوم به داخل المكتبة.
How do we go and do this, and how do we get it down
كيف سنقوم بذلك و نركز عليه
so that it's a cost point that we could afford?
بحيث أن تكلفته تقارب ما يمكننا تحمله
And we sort of picked the price point of 10 cents a page.
و نحن تقريباً وجدنا السعر بحدود 10 سنتات للصفحة
If it's basically the cost of xeroxing to basically digitize, OCR, package it up,
انه بشكل اساسي تكلفة الرقمنة من خلال ماسحة زيروكس, من ثم تحويل الصورة لنص, و توضيبه
make it so that you could download, print and bind it -- the whole shebang --
جعله بحيث يمكن تنزيله, طباعته و تجليده, وكل الباقي
we would have achieved something.
سنكون قد حققنا شيئاً ما
So we started out trying to figure out. How do we get to 10 cents?
لذلك بدأنا بمحاولة معرفة كيف سنصل الى 10 سنت
And we tried these robot things, and they worked pretty well --
و جربنا باستخدام تلك الاشياء الالية و لقد عملت جيداً
sort of these auto-page-turning things.
نوعاً من تقليب الصفحات الآلي
If we can have Mars Rovers, you'd think you could turn pages.
اذا كان بامكاننا الحصول على مستكشفات المريخ, فسوف تظن انه يمكنك تقليب الصفحات
But it actually turns out to be pretty hard to turn pages, and the volume isn't there.
و لكنه في الواقع تبين أن تقليب الصفحات عمل صعب و المجلد ليس هناك
So anyway -- so we ended up making our own book scanner,
لذلك على أية حال, انتهينا بصنع ماسحتنا الضوئية الخاصة
and with two digital, high-grade, professional digital cameras,
و بواسطة كاميرتين احترافيتين عاليتي المستوى
controlled museum lighting, so even if it's a black and white book,
و ضوء المتحف المتحكم به -- لذلك حتى لو كان كتابا أبيض و أسود
you can go and get the proper intonation.
تستطيع الذهاب و الحصول على الدرجة المناسبة
So you basically do a beautiful, respectful job.
و بذلك تكون قد عملت عملاً جميلاً
This is not a fax, this is -- the idea is to do a beautiful job
هذا ليس فاكساً, انه -- الفكرة أن تقوم بعمل جميل
as you're going through these libraries.
بينما تتجول خلال هذه المكتبات
And we've been able to achieve 10 cents a page if we run things in volume.
و استطعنا الوصول لتكلفة 10 سنتات للصفحة اذا قمنا بتطبيق هذا الشيئ على المجلدات
This is what it looks like at the University of Toronto.
هكذا ما يبدو عليه في جامعة تورينتو
And actually, it turns out to, you know, pay a living wage.
و تحول الامر الى عمل بأجر
People seem to love it.
بدا أن الناس تحبه
Yes, it's a little boring, but some people kind of get into the Zen of it.
نعم , انه ممل قليلاً و لكن بعض الناس بدوا و كأنهم من الزن ( طائفة صينية)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And especially if it's kind of interesting books that you care about,
و خاصة اذا كانت نوعاً من الكتب التي تهمك
in languages that you can read.
و بلغة تسطيع قراءتها
We actually have been able to do a pretty good job of this, at getting 10 cents a page.
نحن في الواقع كنا قادرين على اداء عمل جيد جداً بالوصول الى 10 سنتات للصفحة
So 10 cents a page, 300 pages in your average book, 30 dollars a book.
لذلك 10 سنتات للصفحة, 300 صفحة في كتابك الاعتيادي , 30 دولار للكتاب الواحد
The Library of Congress, if you did the whole darn thing --
مكتبة الكونغرس, اذا عملت كل العمل اللعين المطلوب
26 million books -- is about 750 million dollars, right?
26 مليون كتاب -- انه بحدود 750 مليون دولار, اليس كذلك؟
But a million books, I think, actually would be a pretty good start,
و لكن مليون كتاب-- أظنه في الواقع بداية جيدة
and that would cost 30 million dollars. That's not that big a bill.
و ذلك سيكلف 30 مليون دولار. و هذه ليست بالفاتورة الكبيرة
And what we've been able to do is get into libraries.
و ما كنا قادرين على فعله هو الدخول للمكتبات
We've now got eight of these scanning centers in three countries,
و لدينا ثمانية من مراكز المسح في ثلاث دول
and libraries are up for having their books scanned.
و المكتبات على طريق مسح كتبها
The Getty here is moving their books to the UCLA,
غيتتي هنا تنقل كتبها الى UCLA
which is where we have one these scanning centers,
حيث لدينا أحد مراكز المسح الضوئي
and scanning their out-of-copyright books, which is fabulous.
و القيام بمسح كتبهم التي لا تحمل حقوق طباعة, و هو شيئ رائع
So we're starting to get the institutional responsibility.
و بذلك بدأنا بالحصول على مؤسسات تأخذ الأمر على عاتقها
The thing we're missing is the 10 cents.
الشيئ الغائب هو الـ 10 سنت
If we can get the 10 cents, all the rest of it flows.
اذا كان بامكاننا الحصول على 10 سنتات فإن الباقي سيجري
We've scanned about 200,000 books.
لقد قمنا بمسح 200,000 كتاب
Now we're scanning about 15,000 books a month,
و الان نقوم بمسح 15,000 كتاب شهرياً
and it's starting to gear up another factor of two from there.
و لقد بدأ بالتسارع بشكل أسي مضاعف من هناك
So all in all, that's going very well.
لذلك وبشكل اجمالي انه يسير حسناً
And we're starting to move out of the just out-of-copyright
و بدأنا بالخروج من مجرد بدون حقوق نشر
into the out-of-print world.
الى عالم بدون طباعة
So I think of -- we're kind of going from the out-of-copyright, library stuff,
لذلك أظن أننا نخرج من اطار بدون حقوق نشر في المكتبات
and Amazon.com is coming from the in-print world.
و أمازون دوت كوم قادمة من عالم الطباعة
And I think we'll meet in the middle some place,
و أعتقد اننا سنتقابل في منتصف مكان ما
and have the classic thing that you have,
و نحصل على الاشياء الكلاسيكية التي لديك
which is a publishing system and a library system working in parallel.
و الذي هو نظام نشر ونظام مكتبنت يعملان على التوازي
And so we're starting up a program to do out-of-print works, but loaning them.
و لذلك نعمل على برنامج يعمل على عدم الطباعة بل الاعارة
Exactly what loaning means, I'm not quite sure.
ماذا تعني الاعارة تماماً, أنا لست متأكداً
But anyway, loaning out-of-print works from the Boston Public Library,
ولكن على أي حال, اعارة الاعمال الغير مخصصة للطباعة من مكتبة بوسطن العامة
the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute and a few other libraries
معهد علوم المحيطات و مكتبات أخرى قليلة
that are starting to participate in this program,
التي بدأت في الاشتراك في البرنامج
to try out this model of where does a library stop
لتجربة هذا النموذج حيث تتوقف المكتبة
and where does the bookstore take over.
و حيث تتولى متاجر الكتب الأمر
So all in all, it's possible to do this in large scale.
وبشكل اجمالي يمكن عمله بنطاق واسع
We're also going back over microfilm and getting that online.
يمكننا أيضاً العودة بميكرو فيلم و الحصول عليه على الشبكة
So, we can do 10 cents a page, we're going 15,000 books a month
لذلك يمكننا عمل 10 سنتات للصفحة, و نحن نعمل 15000 كتاب في الشهر
and we've got about 250,000 books online,
و لدينا 250,000 كتاب على الشبكة
counting all the other projects that are starting to add in.
مع اعتبار جميع المشاريع التي بدأت بالاضافة
So what I wanted to argue is, books are within our grasp.
لذلك ما أود الجدال حوله أن الكتب بمتناول يدينا
The idea of taking on the whole ball of wax is not that big a deal.
و فكرة تحدي كرة الشمع كلها ليست بالأمر الكبير
Yes, it costs tens of millions, low hundreds of millions,
نعم انها تكلف عشرات الملايين , بضع مئات من الملايين
but one time shot and we've got basically the history of printed literature online.
و لكن بلمحة خاطفة نحصل بشكل أساسي على تاريخ الادب المطبوع على الشبكة
And then, there's business model issues
و عندئذ هنالك مسائل أنماط العمل
about how to try to effectively market it and get it to people.
حول كيفية تسويقها و تقديمها للناس
But it is within our grasp, technologically and law-wise,
و لكن ذلك بمتناولنا من الناحية التقنية و القانونية
at least for the out of print and out of copyright,
خصوصاً بخصوص الاعمال الغير معدة للطباعة أو التي بلا حقوق نشر
we suggest, to be able to get the whole darn thing online.
و نقترح بأن يكون بمقدورنا الحصول على كل هذا على الشبكة
Now let's go for audio, and I'm going to go through these.
دعونا الان نذهب للصوتيات, و أنا سأخوض فيهم
So how much is there?
حسناً , كم هناك؟
Well, as best we can tell, there are about two to three million disks
حسناً, بأفضل ما يمكننا القول, هناك حوالي مليونين أو ثلاثة ملايين قرص
having been published -- so 78s, long-playing records and CDs --
تم نشرها-- لذلك 78 ثانية كزمن تسجيل و اقراص مدمجة
or at least that's the largest archives of published materials
أو على الاقل ذلك الارشيف الاضخم من المواد المنشورة
we've been able to sort of point at.
الذي لدينا اشارة له
It costs about 10 dollars a piece to go and take a disk
يكلفك حوالي 10 دولارات لتذهب و تأخذ قرصاً
and put it online, if you're doing things in volume.
و تضعه على الشبكة اذا كنت تفعل ذلك بالحجم
But we've found that the rights issues are really quite thorny.
و لكن موضوع الحقوق وجدناه شائكاً حقاً
This is a fairly heavily litigated area,
انها منطقة قابلة للمقاضاة بشكل كبير
so we've found that there are niches in the music world
لذلك وجدنا أن هناك كوة في عالم الموسيقا
that aren't served terribly well by the classic commercial publishing system.
لم تخدم بشكل جيد بشكل فظيع بالنظام التقليدي التجاري للنشر
And we've been starting to make these available by going
و بدأنا بجعلها متاحة بالذهاب
and offering shelf space on the Net.
و تأمين مساحة رف على الشبكة
In the United States, it doesn't cost you to give something away. Right?
في الولايات المتحدة لا يكلفك شيئاً للتخلي عن شيئ, صحيح؟
If you give something to a charity or to the public,
اذا أعطيت شيئاً كتبرع أو للعامة
you get a pat on the back and a tax donation --
تحصل على تربيتة على الظهر و هبة ضرائب
except on the Net, where you can go broke.
ما عدا على الشبكة حيث يمكن أن تفلس
If you put up a video of your garage band, and it starts getting heavily accessed,
اذا حملت فيديو عن فرقة الكراج خاصتك و بدأ الدخول اليه يتزايد بشكل كبير
you can lose your guitars or your house.
يمكن ان تخسر غيتاراتك او بيتك
This doesn't make any sense.
و ذلك ليس له معنى
So we've offered unlimited storage, unlimited bandwidth, forever, for free,
لذلك فنحن وفرنا مساحات تخزين غير محدودة, مدى حزمة غير محدود للابد مجاناً
to anybody that has something to share that belongs in a library.
لأي شخص لديه شيئاً ليشاركه في المكتبة
And we've been getting a lot of takers. One is the rock 'n' rollers.
وكنا نحصل على العديد من الآخذين. أحدهم كان روك اند رولرز
The rock 'n' rollers had a tradition of sharing,
الروك اند رولرز لديهم عادة المشاركة
as long as nobody made any money. You could --
طالما أن لا أحد يحصل على المال. يمكنك
concert recordings, it's not the commercial recordings,
بث تسجيلاتك انها ليست التسجيلات التجارية
but concert recordings, started by the Grateful Dead.
ولكن بث التسجيلات بدأ من قبل غريتفول ديد
And we get about two or three bands a day signing up.
ويقوم بالتسجيل في الموقع لدينا تقريباً اثنان او ثلاث فرق في اليوم
They give permission, and we get about 40 or 50 concerts a day.
هم يمنحون السماحية و نحصل يومياً على 40 أو 50 حفلة باليوم
We have about 40,000 concerts, everything the Grateful Dead ever did,
لدينا حوالي 400,000 حفلة كل ما قام الغريتفول ديد بتحميلها
up on the Net, so that people can see it and listen to this material.
على الشبكة بحيث يمكن للناس رؤية وسماع المواد
So audio is possible to put up, but the rights issues are really pretty thorny.
لذلك يمكن رفع الصوت على الشبكة, ولكن مواضيع الحقوق شائكة جداً
We've got a lot of collections now --
حصلنا الان على العديد من المجموعات
a couple hundred thousand items -- and it's growing over time.
مئتي ألف مادة -- و انها تزداد بمرور الوقت
Moving images: if you think of theatrical releases,
تحريك الصور: اذا كنت تظن بتحرير المسرح
there are not that many of them.
ليس لدينا الكثير منهم
As best we can tell, there are about 150,000 to 200,000 movies ever
و بأفضل ما يمكن القول, هناك حوالي 150,000 الى 200,000 فلم
that are really meant for a large-scale theatrical distribution. It's just not that many.
و ذلك حقاً وجد للنشر المسرحي واسع النطاق. انه ليس كثيراً تماماً
But half of those were Indian.
و نصفهم هندي
But anyway, it's doable,
ولكن على أي حال قابلين للتحقيق
but we've only found about a thousand of these things that --
و لكن وجدنا فقط حوالي الالف من هذه الاشياء التي--
to be out of copyright.
ليس لها حقوق نشر
So we've digitized those and made those available.
لذلك قمنا برقمنتهم و جعلهم بمتناول اليد
But we've found that there's lots of other types of movies
و لكن وجدنا ان هناك الكثير من الانواع الاخرى للأفلام
that haven't really seen the light of day -- archival films.
التي لم تر النور بعد -- الافلام الارشيفية
We've found, also, a lot of political films, a lot of amateur films,
و جدنا ايضاً العديد من الافلام السياسية و العديد من افلام الهواة
all sorts of things that are basically needing a home, a permanent home.
كل الأشكال التي بحاجة بشكل أساسي لبيت, لبيت دائم
So we've been starting to make these available and it's grown to be very popular.
لذلك بدأنا بجعل ذلك متاحاً و نما بحيث اصبح شعبياً
We're not quite a YouTube.
نحن لستا تماماً يو تيوب
We tended towards longer-term things
عمدنا لامور اكثر ديمومة
and also things that people can reuse and make into new movies,
و ايضاً اشياء يمكن الناس من اعادة استعمالها في افلام جديدة
which has just been great fun.
الذي كان ممتعاً جداً
Television comes quite a bit larger.
التلفزيون يأتي بشكل اكبر قليلاً
We started recording 20 channels of television 24 hours a day.
بدأنا بتسجيل 20 قناة تلفزيونية لـ 24 ساعة باليوم
It's sort of the biggest TiVo box you've ever seen.
انه نوعا ما أكبر جهاز تايفو قد رأيته أبداً
It's about a petabyte, so far, of worldwide television --
انه حوالي بيدو بايت , نوعا ما تلفزيون عالمي
Russian, Chinese, Japanese, Iraqi, Al Jazeera, BBC, CNN, ABC, CBS, NBC --
روسي, صيني, ياباني, عراقي, الجزيرة, BBC, CNN, ABC, CBS, NBC
24 hours a day.
24 ساعة يومياً
We only put one week up,
وضعنا-- لقد وضعنا فقط اسبوع واحد
which is mostly for cost reasons, which is the 9/11,
بسبب التكاليف التي هي 11/9
sort of from 9/11/2001. For one week, what did the world see?
نو عاً من 9/11/2001 لمدة اسبوع واحد, ماذا شاهد العالم؟
CNN was saying that Palestinians were dancing in the streets.
سي ان ان تقول ان الفلسطينيين كانوا يرقصون في الشوارع
Were they? Let's look at the Palestinian television and find out.
أحقاً ذلك؟ دعونا نر التلفزيون الفلسطيني و نحكم
How can we have critical thinking without being able to quote
كيف يمكن ان يكون لدينا التفكير المتأزم بدون القدرة على الاقتباس
and being able to compare what happened in the past?
و نكون قادرين على مقارنة ما يحصل بالماضي
And television is dreadfully unrecorded and unquotable,
و التلفاز غير قابل للاقتباس أو التسجيل بشكل مخيف
except by Jon Stewart, who does a fabulous job.
ما عدا جون ستيوارت الذي ادى عملاً جيداً
So anyway, television is, I would suggest, within our grasp.
لذلك على أية حال, التلفاز هو كما اقترح بمتناول ايدينا
So 15 dollars per video hour, and also about 100 dollars to 150 dollars per celluloid hour,
لذلك 15 دولار لساعة الفيديو و ايضاً حوالي 100 دولار الى 150 دولار لساعة التسجيل السينمائي
we're able to go and get materials online very inexpensively
يمكننا الذهاب و الحصول على المواد بشكل رخيص جداً
and have them up on the Net.
و رفعهم على الشبكةَ
And we've got, now, a lot of these materials.
و لدينا الان الكثير من هذه المواد
So we've got about 100,000 pieces up there.
لدينا حوالي 100,000 قطعة هناك
So books, music, video, software. There's only 50,000 titles of it.
لذلك الكتب, الموسيقى, الفيديو, البرامج الكومبيوترية-- هناك فقط 50,000 عنوان لها
Mostly the issues there are legal issues and breaking copy protections.
و معظم المسائل هي قانونية و مسائل كسر حماية النسخ
But we've worked through some of those,
و لكن عملنا على بعضهم
but we've still got real problems in Washington.
ولكن ما زلنا نواجه مشاكل كبيرة في واشنطون
Well, we're best known as the World Wide Web.
حسناً نحن معروفون بأفضل شكل كشبكة الانترنت
We've been archiving the World Wide Web since 1996.
نحن كنا نأرشف الشبكة العالمية منذ 1996
We take a snapshot of every website and all of the pages on it, every two months.
نأخذ لقطة من كل موقع و كل صفحاته كل شهرين
And actually, it's really been pioneered by Alexa Internet,
و في الواقع, كان موقع أليكسا رائداً
which donates this collection to the Internet Archive.
الذي تبرع بالمجموعة لأرشيف الشبكة
And it's been growing along for the last 11 years, and it's a fantastic resource.
و كان ينمو للسنوات الـ 11 الأخيرة و كان مورداً رائعاً
And we've made a Wayback Machine
و صنعنا الة اعادة الزمن
that you can then go and see old websites kind of the way they were.
بحيث يمكنك الذهاب و رؤية المواقع القديمة كما كانت نوعاً ما
If you go and search on something -- this is Google.com,
اذا بحثت عن شيئ ما, و هذا هو غوغل دوت كوم
the different versions of it that we have,
الاصدارات المختلفة منه و التي لدينا
this is what it looks like when it was an alpha release,
هكذا بدا عند الاصدار التجريبي الأول
and this is what it looked like at Stanford.
وهكذا بدا في ستانفورد
So anyway, you've got basically an idea of where things came from.
لذلك و على أي حال, حصلت بشكل مبدئي على فكرة من أين أتت الأشياء
Mostly, people want to see their old stuff out of this.
معظم الناس يودون رؤية أشياءهم القديمة خارج هذا
If there's one thing that we want to learn from the Library of Alexandria version one,
اذا كان هناك ما نريد تعلمه من مكتبة الاسكندرية الاولى
which is probably best known for burning,
و التي عرفت بحريقها
is, don't just have one copy.
فهو: لا تحتفظ بنسخة واحدة فقط
So we've started to -- we've made another copy of all of this
لذلك بدأنا-- قمنا بعمل نسخة من كل ذلك
and we actually put it back in the Library of Alexandria.
و حقيقة قمنا بوضعها في مكتبة الاسكندرية
So this is a picture of the Internet Archive at the Library of Alexandria.
و هذه صورة لأرشيف الانترنت في مكتبة الاسكندرية
And we now have also another copy building up in Amsterdam.
و نحن الآن نملك نسخة أخرى نقوم ببنائها في امستردام
So, we should put it in the San Andreas Fault Line in San Francisco,
لذلك علينا وضعها في سان اندرياس فولت لاين في سان فرانسيسكو
flood zone in Amsterdam and in the Middle East. Right, so anyway ...
منطقة فيضان في امستردام و الشرق الأوسط صحيح؟ لذلك على أية حال
so we're hedging our bets here.
لذلك نحن نصون رهاننا هنا
If we go and put it in a couple more places, I think we'll be in good shape.
اذا ذهبنا ووضعناه في مكانيين آخرين’ أظن اننا سنكون بحال جيدة
There's a political and social question out of this.
هنالك سؤال اجتماعي و سياسي من ذلك
Is all of this, as we go digital, is it going to be public or private?
هل كل ذلك و نحن نسير في الرقمنة , هل ستذهب باتجاه ان تكون عامة أو خاصة؟
There's some large companies that have seen this vision,
هناك بعض الشركات الضخمة التي رأت هذه الرؤية
that are doing large-scale digitization,
انهم يذهبون باتجاه الرقمنة على نطاق واسع
but they're locking up the public domain.
و لكن يقفلون النطاق العام
The question is, is that the world that we really want to live in?
السؤال هو: هل ذلك هو العالم الذي نريد العيش فيه
What's the role of the public versus the private as things go forward?
ماذا يحكم العام ضد الخاص مع تقدم الامور
How do we go and have a world where we both have libraries
كيف نذهب و نمتلك العالم حيث كلانا لديه مكتبة
and publishing in the future, just as we basically benefited as we were growing up?
و ننشر بالمستقبل, تماما مع كوننا مستفيدين مع نمونا
So universal access to all knowledge --
اي الولوج الكوني لكل المعرفة
I think it can be one of the greatest achievements of humankind,
اعتقد انه يمكن ان يكون أعظم ما توصل اليه الجنس البشري
like the man on the moon, or the Gutenberg Bible, or the Library of Alexandria.
مثل الانسان على القمر أو انجيل يوحنا أو مكتبة الاسكندرية
It could be something that we're remembered for,
انه شيئ يمكن أن نذكر به
for millennia, for having achieved.
بألفية تحقيقه
And as I said before, I'll end with something
و كما قلت سابقاً سأنتهي بشيئ
that's carved above the door of the Carnegie Library.
محفور فوق مكتبة كارنيجي--
Carnegie -- one of the great capitalists of this country --
كارنيجي-- واحد من الرأسماليين العظماء في هذا البلد
carved above his legacy, "Free to the People."
محفور فوق ارثه: " مجاناً للناس"
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم